<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>M. le Hucher minister of Amyens in France compelled to fly from the pure word of holy write; strucke dumme; and made to runne away Vppon the subiect of the B. Sacrament of the altar. By F. Francis Veron of the Society of Iesus, encountring him with the Bible of Geneua only. In the presence of the Duke de Longueuille. VVith a briefe and easie meanes, by which each Catholike may, in like manner, put to flight any minister or sectarie. Sent from Sieur de la Tour one of the sayd Dukes gentlemen, to Sieur de Rotois, gentleman of the Kings game.</title>
            <title>Adrian Hucher ministre d'Amyens, mis à l'inquisition des passages de la Bible de Genève. English</title>
            <author>Véron, François, 1575-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24675.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14357)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 584:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>M. le Hucher minister of Amyens in France compelled to fly from the pure word of holy write; strucke dumme; and made to runne away Vppon the subiect of the B. Sacrament of the altar. By F. Francis Veron of the Society of Iesus, encountring him with the Bible of Geneua only. In the presence of the Duke de Longueuille. VVith a briefe and easie meanes, by which each Catholike may, in like manner, put to flight any minister or sectarie. Sent from Sieur de la Tour one of the sayd Dukes gentlemen, to Sieur de Rotois, gentleman of the Kings game.</title>
                  <title>Adrian Hucher ministre d'Amyens, mis à l'inquisition des passages de la Bible de Genève. English</title>
                  <author>Véron, François, 1575-1649.</author>
                  <author>Catcher, Edward, 1584?-1624?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Widow of L. Kellam,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed [Douai :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by D.V., i.e. Edward Catcher alias Burton, of: Véron, Francois.  Adrian Hucher ministre d'Amyens, mis à l'inquisition des passages de la Bible de Genève, ..</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 15400.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 15400 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; copy trimmed at foot, affecting imprint, catchwords and signatures.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Le Hucher, Adrien --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7766:1"/>
            <p>M. LE HVCHER MINISTER OF AMYENS IN FRANCE COMPELLED to fly from the pure word of Holy write; ſtrucke dumme; and made to runne away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vppon the ſubiect of the B. Sacrament of the Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By F. FRANCIS VERON of the Society of IESVS, encountring him with the Bible of Geneua only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the preſence of the Duke de Longueuille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVith a briefe and eaſie meanes, by which each Catholicke may, in like manner, put to flight any Miniſter or Sectarie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sent from Sieur de la Tour one of the ſayd Dukes Gentlemen, to Sieur de Rotois, Gentleman of the Kings game.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7766:2"/>
            <head>Explication of the Title.</head>
            <p>This Conference was held three ſeuerall times. In the firſt the Father of the Society; compelled the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to abandone the pure word of the holie ſcripture; In the 2. he putt him to ſilence; In the 3. he made him runne away.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>Testimony of the ſaid conference.</head>
            <p>It is ſigned by the Father of the Society; by the Duke of Longueuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Gentlemen who accompanying theyr Lord were preſent therat; and in parte by the Miniſter, which refuſed to ſubcribe to that, which putt him moſt to confuſion. The ſubcriptions follow in theyr proper place.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:7766:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo</hi> things there are (good Reader) which made me (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of thy eternall good) to turne for thy vſe this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle treatiſe into our language. The one the breuity and pleaſure it yealdeth, the other the eaſines and perſpicuity, with which it confuteth, it inſtructeth. The firſt ſuteth well to that lazy humour, which hereſy hath brought into our country, wherby men haue little gust to read ought, that concernes their ſoules, and ſcarſe ought of that, vnles it be well ſeaſoned with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary delight. The other (ſuppoſing thy capacity, and affection to truth, which if affection miſleade me not, is equall to that of moſt Nations, and by hereſy I hope not maliciouſly peruerted, or at least not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly obſtinate therin) makes me preſume thou wilt eaſily ſee, and quickly leaue that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7766:3"/> blind mans maze, of the falſly pure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended word, wherin thou haſt beene long ledde round. Both of them, by Gods aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, promiſſe vnto me no little fruite of this ſmall worke, which is that I hartely deſyre for thy ſoules good, and Gods grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy welwiller in IESVS CHRIST. D. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:7766:3"/>
            <head>A LETTER OF M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. DE LA TOVR GENTLEMAN TO THE DVKE OF LONGVEVILLE. <hi>VVritten vnto M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. de Rotois Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Kings game.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR the ardent zeale I know you haue of the good and glory of our Religion, makes me ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you wil receaue a ſingular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the relation of a priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, had of late in the preſence of my Lord the Duke of Longue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uille and his followers, of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques de Boniuet, of the Lady de Bourcq &amp; diuers others aſwell Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks as Sectaries, between Father
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7766:4"/> Francis Veron of the Society of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS, preacher for this preſent in the great Church of this Citty, &amp; M. le Hucher Miniſter of the Caluiniſts in the ſame place, touching that point of our Faith, of the body of the so<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God in the Sacrament of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. The ſaid Father agreeing to deale with that Miniſter by the Bible of Geneua only, and the Confeſſion of faith of the reformed. This confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence hath had three ſeſſions, at the firſt I was not preſent, not being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed of the ſame. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the beginning of the ſecond, the actes of the former ſeſſion were read, alowed &amp; auowed by both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as authenticall. Wherfore I will make recitall of that which paſſed in the ſight of my Lord, &amp; vs that were attending on him, beſides a great multitude of diuerſe of the one, and the other Religion. The ſaid Father on the morrow after the laſt confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which was Sunday, made an ample narration of the three paſſed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7766:4"/> meetings to aboue eight thowſand perſones, aſſembled in the Church of our Lady to heare his ſermon. The moſt heerof is ſigned as you will ſee after, wherfore no man can iuſtlie call in queſtion a matter ſo cleerly teſtified.</p>
            <p>Our Deuine atchieued three fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous victories. For the Miniſter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing promiſed conformably to the 31. and 5. articles of theyr Confeſſion of their faith, to shew by the pure word of the Bible, that we erred in that beleefe we haue, that the body of our Lord is in the Euchariſt, he was conſtrained in the firſt ſeſſion and againe in the entrance vnto the ſecond trial, to ſly from his fortreſſe of the pure word, of force diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the pure ſcripture of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua: and withall aknowledged and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed, that there was no expreſſe text in all the ſcripture, euen by the Geneua tranſlation, which, ſetting a ſide all illations, did condemne vs of errour. But (quoth the Miniſter) by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7766:5"/> neceſſary conſequence out of the pure worde of God I will make it cleare that you do erre.</p>
            <p>The night comming on made our combatant ceaſe the purſuite, &amp; not driue him farther, who already shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred himſelf within the ruinous edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Conſequence. The Father told me, that it was not of ſmall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to make the Sectaries clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee &amp; confeſſe, that they haue not for themſelues the pure ſcripture, but only certain conſequences, for (quoth he) the cauſe that makes ſo many to beginne, and continue in their reuolt from Gods Church, is for that they perſuade themſelues, that they haue on their ſides the pure word of God; for ſo ſaith the 5. article of their Confeſſion, that they admitt nothing for the rule of faith, but the pure word: &amp; they do veryly ſuppoſe that that Confeſſion conteineth nothing, but that which is in the pure worde. After the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of that paſſed before, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7766:5"/> Miniſter at the ſecond ſeſſion was admitted to deduce his neceſſary conſequence, by which he would demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrate how farre we wandred from the truth. He firſt fetched long vagaries round about, afterward the Father ſo dexterouſly put him beſide all his proofes, &amp; in briefe brought him to ſuch pangues, that for the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall propoſition he had nothing to ſay againſt the Father, but, ô you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to much; after which he became alltogeather ſpeechles, as I wil more largely declare her after. Certes you would haue been extraordinarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created to behold, how he that ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while made profeſſion to proue by the pure word of God that we were Idolaters, in lieu of the pure word, had not a word to help himſelf, ſaue this only, that the Ieſuite denied to much wee I am ſure had good ſport therin. Ours which had thus chaſed the Miniſter, ſtill put him to theſe pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues for a long time ſtill vrging him thus. M. Miniſter prooue your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7766:6"/> Neither did he omitt to ſignifie plainly and alowde to the whole aſſemblie, to what exigents the poore Miniſter was brought to, who ſuſtained the Confeſſion of the faith of the reformed Religion, and bragged to diſcouer by the pure word our errours. Had not the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Miniſters cauſe been ſuch as it was, I should haue had compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to haue ſeen him in that plight, and ſo oppreſſed. He deſired they would giue him that night for reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite, and to thinke vppon it; but the Father denied him; he alleaged he was ſuddainly ſurpriſed, the other replied that he had had all the night, and morning before for his proofe of that conſequence. It was not neede to take pitty of the Miniſter, for his fellow Sectaries had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſeration of him; all of them round about me beganne to change coulour, the Elders and Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents ſtood as it were aſtonished, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded. You may coniecture ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7766:6"/> whether we were ioyfull thereat or no Alas (ſaid one) the poore Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter wants a Chirurgian to open him a vayne. This victory was more notorious by this which followeth. The conquerour exacted of the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisshed to ſubſcribe to the Acts of this conference, according to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord made between them. A lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table caſe! that the ouercome muſt ſubſcribe to the actes of his owne condemnation. He refuſed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his promiſſe. The Father af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many inſtant vrgings of him in vaine, turned towards my Lord, and demaunded iuſtice; that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſigne according as he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. The Miniſter deſired fauour, beſeeching him often that he would not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund him to ſubſcribe, after many prayers adding theſe wordes. I know how much it ſtands me vppon not to ſigne, for if I do ſo, all will be published: and the Churches (you vnderſtand his meaning at leaſt his lamenting voice diſcouered his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7766:7"/> intention) the poore congregations (he should ſay) of the pure refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation will be ſcandalized therat. The Father hauing before deſired one of ours to shutt the doore, leaſt the Miniſter should runne away, bid him conſult with his Elders, and Superintendents, whether it were expedient to ſigne the actes or no: for which cauſe drawing them apart it was reſolued that he should not ſigne them. I will ſend you short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more at large this debate, which laſted three quarters of an howre. In fine, with the conſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they graunted him this fauour that he should not ſubſcribe, but with theſe two conditions: the firſt that he should ſubſcribe the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row after; the ſecond that he should continew the diſpute. By this refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall to ſubſcribe vnto the Actes, it is apparent how notable the victorie was on our parte.</p>
            <p>In the third encounter our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion gott a third victory, but in an
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7766:7"/> other kind; will you knowe what? The Miniſter shamefully rann away. He was not willing to be laid againe a gaſping as before, and therfore thought it better not to inter into the liſtes, as I will declare afterward. It was giuen out that the Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendentes had expreſlie forbidd him to venture himſelfe with him, who before had vſed him ſo vnmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for they well ſaw the confuſion like to follow therof, to the great detriment of their Churches.</p>
            <p>Your Religious minde makes me preſume you take great delight in this chace; I will therfore giue you the whole narration. But yett be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand I wil shew you a new ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of hunting, which, though you be moſt skilfull in that ſport, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance vnknowne vnto you. The fashion is ſpeedy, with little paines, and moſt effectuall, by which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe our Huntſman hath ſo happily ſeazed on his pray: and by the ſame I aſſure my ſelf, that euen we whoſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7766:8"/> profeſſion is to be better at our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon then our penne, may chace out of breath any Miniſter ſoeuer, and make any Sectarie ſee how groſllie he is abuſed. This I haue compiled as a thing I knowe to be true, and wherof I meane to ſerue my ſelf on all occaſions. In this Conference I haue had experience of this practiſe, for therein was held no other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode; &amp; to ſatisfy your deſire, who I knowe are curious to learne this new manner of hunting, you may read this which followeth, the like wherof was ſent vnto the Miniſter as a letter of defiance. Read it ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. To me it ſeemes moſt efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and as eaſy. Wee ſhall all prooue hunters of theſe black beaſtes, the Miniſters I meane of the pretended Religion. I would to God we could ſo chace away not their perſons, but their errours, that we could purge all France thereof. This I now ſend you laid downe at large, you shall short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue the particulars of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7766:8"/> aboue mentioned, in which you will ſee it practiſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="means_of_persuasion">
            <head>A BREEFE AND EASIE meanes by vvhich each one though ignorant of deuinity, may by the ſole Bible either of Geneua, or any other, shevv apperently to any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister hovv farre he is deceaued, and to each Caluinist, hovv in all and euery point of the pretended reformation he is abuſed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>NCOVNTRING a Miniſter or anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Caluiniſt, you shall proceed in this manner.</p>
            <p>You haue in the 31. article of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of your faith theſe words. <hi>In our dayes, in which the estate of the Church was diſſolued, God hath raiſed men after an extraordinary manner to repaire
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7766:9"/> of new the Church which was ruinated and deſolate.</hi> Thus, you ſay, your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion comes to reforme our errours.</p>
            <p>In the 5. article are theſe words. <hi>The word which is contayned in theſe bookes</hi> (he ſpake of the bookes of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture) <hi>is the rule of all truth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all that is neceſſary for the ſeruice of God, and our ſaluation; Neither is it lawfull for men, no nor for Angells, to adde, diminish, or change. VVhence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that neither Antiquitie, nor Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, nor Multitude, nor humane wiſdome nor Definitions, nor Inhibitions, nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, nor Decrees, nor Councels, nor Reuelations, nor Miracles may be oppoſed to the ſaid holy Scriptures, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie all thinges ar to be examined; ruled, and reformed by them.</hi> Theſe are the wordes of this article.</p>
            <p>So that in the one and the other article me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned togeather, you ſay that you, or your Religion, or your Miniſters (take your choiſe) are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſent from God, to illuminate vs with the light of truth, &amp; to shew
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7766:9"/> vs our errours and that by the ſole, and pure word of God contained in the holy Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt I might examine the conditions of theſe Reformers you thruſt vpon vs. And vntill you shew me your letter patents and commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I may iuſtly refuſe to ſubmitt my ſelf to be reformed by you. What body politicque will allow the title of Reformour of their Lawes, and Cuſtomes (according to which they haue hitherto proceeded in their gouernment) in one who should ſay he was ſent from the King for that purpoſe, but had no Commiſſion to shew for the ſame? Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in curteſy I do freely admitt you to the dignity and title of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, &amp; am content to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by you in the truth, and to be reformed in whatſoeuer I do erre. I would know of you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. According to what rules, by what line doth it pleaſe you to ſtraighten me, to shew my errours,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7766:10"/> and illuminate me with the truth of the Goſpell? You make me anſweare in the 5. article aboue cited, that you will do all this according to the pure word of God, ſett downe in Holie writt, laying aſide, <hi>All Antiquity, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Multitude, humane VViſdome, Definitions, Inhibitions, Proclamations, Lawes, Councels, Reuelations, Miracles.</hi> I could refuſe this fashion of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. For why should I not, togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Scripture, help my ſelf with all other rules to diſcerne the truth thereby? Eſpecially ſince that the Scripture no where ſaith, that it ſelf alone is the rule of all verity. It ſeemes hard to me to renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce al An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, Miracles, &amp; all the reſt before ſett downe. Neuertheles to ioyne with you in Conference, I am content of my owne accord to graunt you the title of Reformer by the pure written word, &amp; am ready to renounce al thoſe rules ſpecified, prouided allwaies that you keepe your promiſe, to witt that you shew
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7766:10"/> me my errours, by the pure Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There are diuers tranſlations of the Scriptures; by which, I pray you, will you pleaſe to reforme me? Perchance you inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by that of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua. I might iuſtly refuſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by that Bible; being it is ſo curtalled in diuers places, corrupted, and changed: Yet to haue your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation I wil do you this third fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. I am content to open my eyes and follow your Religion, if you shew my by the pure word contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Geneua verſion, both the truth of the faith you Euangelize, &amp; allſo my errours. I haue donne you three great fauours. 1. to graunt you the title of a Reformer. 2. to be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former by the pure word. The third to make this triall by the pure word of the Geneua verſion. But looke you bring me nothing els but the pure word; for if in ſteede of it you shift me of with your interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you forſake the Confeſſion of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7766:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> your faith, &amp; breake the couenants made betweene vs. For I am not ſo vnaduiſed to renounce all Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Councells, Miracles and the reſt, for your interpretations and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Agreeably to this, to your owne promiſe, &amp; that which is ſett downe in your 5. article, I demaund two things at your hands. Firſt that you shew me by the pure word the truth of all thoſe articles which you will haue me to beleeue: which I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to do, if I ſee them in the Bible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of Geneua. Secondly that by the ſame pure word you shew me my errours. Both of theſe I demand, for both of theſe you profeſſe to do when as you ſay, that <hi>the Scripture is the rule of all truth,</hi> and you acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no other. For put the caſe I ſhould erre in my faith, I would be loth to leaue that, to follow a worſe. No wiſe man, I take it, though his horſe haue but one eye wil make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge for another that is blind; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7766:11"/> therfore to ſee by the pure word the truth of yours. Which you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not refuſe to do, for you are ſent to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate vs, &amp; shew vs the truth. To be plaine therfore, my firſt demaund is, that you shew me by the pure word the Articles of your Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by which I muſt be illuminated, and made to knowe the right way.</p>
            <p>In the 36. and 37. article you ſay that <hi>we receaue by faith,</hi> or, to vſe your ordinary termes, <hi>by the mouth of faith the body of our Lord.</hi> Shew me this in the pure word, &amp; that the ſupper is the figure of his body. Through all the Geneua Bible I find not ſo much as mention made of the mouth of faith, neither do I finde any talke of a figure in thoſe places, where it ſpeakes of the ſupper. Shew me but this, &amp; I will ſtraight beleeue it and abiure my former Religion. This if you do not, I muſt needs hold you, as you ar, for impoſtours.</p>
            <p>In the 11. article it is ſaid. <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne doth continually remaine after
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7766:12"/> Baptiſme in aſmuch as it is a fault, howbeit the children of God are freed from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation due for the ſame, he through his gracious goodnes not imputing it vnto them.</hi> Shew me this in the pure word of Geneua.</p>
            <p>In the 24. article. <hi>Ieſus Christ is giuen vs for our ſole Aduocate,</hi> The ſtrife between vs is about that worde <hi>Sole,</hi> shew me that in the Geneua Bible.</p>
            <p>In the 20. article. We beleeue <hi>we are made partakers of that iuſtice</hi> (to witt of Chriſtians) <hi>by faith alone.</hi> All the controuerſie lyeth in that word <hi>alone,</hi> and whether workes donne in the faith of Chriſt be neceſſary; shew me that worde <hi>alone</hi> in theſe places, where mention is made of workes donne in the faith of IESVS CHRIST, and not in theſe places, where the Iudaicall workes of the law are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from Chriſtian iuſtification, for of theſe only do we diſpute. I haue turned the Bible for the places cited in the margent for theſe arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but cannot find any of theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7766:12"/> in the pure word.</p>
            <p>Hauing quitt your hands well, in shewing me the truth of that which you deſire I should beleeue, shew me as well that other thing I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, to witt the errours of thoſe articles which I now beleeue.</p>
            <p>The articles of my faith are for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample (to omitt that point of the B. Sacrement allready ſpoken of) <hi>That there is a Purgatory, Interceſsion of Saints, Auricular Confeſsion, and the like. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Sanctity of Pilgrimages, of Religious vowes.</hi> Againſt which in your 24. article you ſay. <hi>Interceſſion of Saints is an abuſe, Purgatorrie an illuſion and ſo of religious vowes, Pilgrimages and the like.</hi> Shew me my errour in theſe points, &amp; that out of the pure word. In your margent I find no text cited, which is a shrewd ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that you haue none. Perchance you wil aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare that it ſufficeth for a proofe of errour in theſe points, that they are not found in the holy ſcripture, becauſe nothing muſt be beleeued
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7766:13"/> but that which is in the ſcripture. My reply to this is to know of you whether this propoſition. <hi>That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing must be beleeued which is not in the holy ſcripture</hi> be found in the pure word of God or. If it be not, then you M. Miniſter in propounding this propoſition to be beleeued of me, do falſify your owne fayth, and breake your promiſe; for you ſayd you wold not admitt any other rule of truth but the ſcripture, which is in effect, that you will bring forth nothing but that which is in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and now you thruſt vpon me this propoſition, which is not there to be found, &amp; this as a fundamental propoſition vpon which ar builded many others: but if this propoſition be in the pure word, shew it; but take heede you bring nothing, but the pure word.</p>
            <p>When by the pure word you shall shew me the truth of your articles, and the falshood of mine, as hath been ſaid before, I am ready forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7766:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> to acknowledge my errour, &amp; to embrace your faith. But remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I pray you, your promiſe, that you would by the pure word shew the truth of your faith and my er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; and that I renounced all anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Councels, Miracles, Inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Lawes, viſions vppon theſe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes only, and no other. Looke that in ſteed of the pure word, you do not shift me of with your interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or your owne conſequences, for either that interpretation is in the Scripture, or no; if it be there, bring forth the Scripture: and that the Scripture ſaie of each propoſition you interprete, that it is ſo to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, &amp; that you only are the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane to pronounce the ſame, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you leaue your owne faith, and forge an other to your owne liking, of which I shall argue with you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the like ſorte; &amp; beſides that you breake your promiſe. I ſhould be eſteemed of ſmall iudgment if I forſake Councells, Miracles Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7766:14"/> and the reſt for your interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>If the Miniſter pretend to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant his interpretation by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſage of the Scripture, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample if he vrge that thoſe words <hi>(This is my body)</hi> muſt not be taken properlie but figuratiuelie, becauſe theſe others <hi>(I ame a vine)</hi> haue ſuch a ſignification: You shall aske him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Before you paſſe to any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he haue any plaine text, which abſtracting from all interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation doth condemne vs of errour: for example in that point of the B. Sacrament, in which we beleeue there is the true body of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. If he haue any, lett him bring that which is cleare and plaine, and leaue that which is obſcure: if he haue none, make him to confeſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, that he hath no place out of the pure word, by which, without his interpretation, he can conuince vs of errour; and heere you muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7766:14"/> on this point, till he haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed this. After this Confeſſion comming to the interpretation he giues, you shall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Demaunde, if the Scripture ſay that theſe words <hi>(This is my Body)</hi> are to be interpreted by theſe <hi>(I am a vine)</hi> or no. If it ſay ſo, lett him shew the place; If not, then the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter breaks his couenants, &amp; doth not ſerue as an organe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only. And heere the Miniſter is in little eaſe, neither can he, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out renouncing their Confeſſion, which profeſſeth to allow of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to rule them, but pure Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, paſſe any farther. Neither is it needfull to purſue the matter anie farther, this being concluded, for heere haue you the Miniſter in the ſtocks; and perchaunce it will be better to keepe the Miniſtre in this traunce ſpeechles, then to paſſe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Yet if you deſire an other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, &amp; that he, which encountreth the Caluiniſt, be learned or expert
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7766:15"/> in the Scripture, he may, after the confeſſion of the two former.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Harken to the interpretation the Miniſtre brings, and aunſweare theſe proofes he alleageth for that interpretation. But allwaies remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that the Caluiniſt, by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, is come to inſtruct vs, &amp; conſequently bound to prooue his interpretation; for vs, if it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince not, it ſufficeth to deny, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obligation to giue any reaſons for our deniall: for by thoſe the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter will finde meanes to ſlippe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and will not be ſo quicklie caught: he will ſeek many by-waies, therfore as much as may be ſtoppe his paſſage. Behold how you are to proceede, when the Miniſter vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to shew our pretended errours by text of Scripture, without conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences or illations.</p>
            <p>When he will diſcouer our errours by ſome conſequence, which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth out of the pure word of God for example, we beleeue that <hi>the body
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7766:15"/> of our Lord is in the B. Sacrament of the Altar:</hi> he will prooue by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence deduced out of the pure and ſole Scripture, that he is not there, after this manner. In the 3. of the Actes, it is ſaid, that <hi>Heauen muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine him vntill the Conſummation of the world,</hi> therfore he is not on the earth. Behold his ſillogiſme. <hi>That body which is in heauen is not on the earth, the body of Ieſus Chriſt is in heauen, therfore it is not on the earth.</hi> He muſt put his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this forme. 1. Before you come to aunſwere his argument, you muſt aske the Miniſter if he haue any plaine text, which without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence doth condemne vs of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in this point, or no? If he haue, lett him bring it out, who profeſſeth to reforme vs by the pure word; If he haue not, make him confeſſe that he hath no plaine text, by which (his conſequence ſett a part) we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced of errour; &amp; heere you muſt ſtay, and exact this confeſſion of the Miniſter before you paſſe farther.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7766:16"/> Hauing made the Miniſter acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this, though you may content your ſelf with this victory (whereby you make him renounce the 5. arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of their Confeſſion of faith, and haue ouerthrowen that piller which detaines moſt of the Sectaries, who follow that part in their errours; who imagine they haue on their ſide the pure word of God, and that they builde vpon the Scripture only) and peraduenture it wil be better to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no farther, to the end to make it eccho oftener in the eares of theſe who are abuſed by them: Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he that will continew the chace, and hauing rowzed the deere from his lodge purſue him farther.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Giuing the Miniſter leaue to deduce his conſequence, after the deduction thereof, the Catholicque muſt not ſtraight examine the truth of the ſame, nor shew ſo quickly that it is falſe; but firſt lay hold on him, and make him shew, that his conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is deduced out of the only
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7766:16"/> pure word of holy Scripture, as he promiſſed to deduce the ſame, and his 5. article doth oblige him. You muſt therfore proceede in this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion. It is a thing vndoubted, and knowen to all, that euery conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to be good, muſt be inferred out of two propoſitions; If then one of thoſe two, out of which the Miniſter deduceth his conſequence, be not in the Scripture, (as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth ordinarily in the arguments of the aduerſary againſt vs) heere you muſt demurr, and make it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that the aduerſarie heere abandonnes his Confeſſion of fayth, and fayles of his promiſſe, in not shewing our pretended errour by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence deduced out of the pure and only Scripture. For example, in the ſyllogiſme before ſett downe. <hi>That body which is in heauen is not on the earth, the body of Ieſus Chriſt is in heauen, therfore it is not on the earth:</hi> you shall examine the Miniſter, whether the firſt propoſition of this argument be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7766:17"/> in the pure word, or no. If it be, lett him shew it. Cleere it is, it is not there, but it is a philoſophicall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, wherfore the Miniſter, which deduceth his conſequence out of that, and the ſecond adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which is in the 3. of the Actes, doth not proue my errour by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence deduced out of the pure word, but by conſequence deduced out of Philoſophy, and out of the word of God, and maketh ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith, as are deduced out of Philoſophy or Ariſtotle. 2. You muſt declare, that euery conſequence muſt be deduced out of two propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, placed in the true forme of a ſyllogiſme, and that the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is inferred both from the propoſitions, and from the forme of the ſyllogiſme; of which forme the Scripture ſpeakes nothing, nor preſcribes any rules about that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but only Ariſtotle, and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy. Wherfore the Miniſter in proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his conſequence, is not foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7766:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> vpon the Scripture alone, which treates not of formes of conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And becauſe it belongs to Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, to iudge if the conſequence be good or no, the Miniſter building vpon conſequence, muſt admitt for his iudge, in the controuerſies of our fayth, not the pure Scripture, but Ariſtotle: or els at leaſt chooſe for vmpyre in this cauſe the word of God, together with Ariſtotle. 3. You muſt demaund of the Miniſter, if the Scripture do teach that one muſt beleeue as an article of faith, not only that which the Scripture ſaith, but alſo that, which by neceſſary conſequence followeth therevpon, or no? if he ſay ſo, make him shew the text, which without doubt he cannot throughout the whole bible: if no ſuch be founde, then doth the Miniſter build his articles of fayth vpon a propoſition, which is not in the pure word, to witt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this. <hi>That that which followeth out of Scripture by neceſſary conſequence, must
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7766:18"/> be beleeued as an article of ſaith.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Scripture frames no ſuch article, but the Miniſter only, and that not by the pure Scripture, but by humane reaſon: from which notwithſtanding in his 5. Article he diſclaimed wholy. For he wold haue vs take at his handes for an article of faith that propoſition, which by conſequence followeth out of the Scripture, though the termes of that propoſition, deduced out of Scripture for an article of fayth, be not there ſett downe. Hence is it that all the articles of the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe ſectaries, which are founded vpon a conſequence, are not articles of fayth, being that they haue not for them theyr only rule of truth, the ſole Scripture. Heere againe you muſt hold him. They will ſay perauenture that IESVS Chriſt, and the Apoſtles proued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges by conſequence. I graunt it. But in ſo doing, they themſelues made new Scriptures, or holy write:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7766:18"/> which priuiledge I thinke the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter haue not. But they neuer taught that the Scripture, which they alledged, was the ſingular and ſole rule of all truth, and that they ſpake not but by the mouth of the Scripture, as theſe Pretenders pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and thyr poore flocke (which thinke they are as good as theyr wordes) perſuade themſelues.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If he that buckle with the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter be learned, and will, after he hath often driuen the deere from his fortreſſe of the pure worde, courſe him alonge the plaine champion of humane and philoſophicall reaſons (though, according to my aduiſe, it be ordinarily more expedient, to content our ſelues with that before ſett downe) for to cure him, if it be poſſible, after the aboue ſaid he may paſſe to the examen of the truth, or falshod of his conſequence: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the propoſitions, from which it is deduced (be they taken from philoſophy or holy writt) be true
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7766:19"/> or falſe; and whether the forme of the argument be according to the rules of Philoſophy, and ſo deny that which the Miniſter aſſumed falſly. Still hauing in minde that the Miniſter is putt to the proofe, not the Catholick, who beares the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne of the party inſtructed; &amp; be ſure not to change that perſonne. For the drift of all the Miniſters fetches is, to vnload himſelf of that obligation to prooue his conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: which he will bring to paſſe by this ſleight, if he can make him, that defends, the diſputant. For example. In the argument propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>That body which is in heauen, is not on the earth; The body of Ieſus Chriſt is in heauen; Therfore it is not on the earth.</hi> You shall deny the firſt propoſition, and lett the Miniſter prooue it. If that his proofes come on to long, &amp; he enter to farre into Philoſophicall quiddities, lett the Catholicke note that it is in his free choice, to curbe the Miniſter short when he liſteth;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7766:19"/> demaunding him, if all the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions which he hath brought to prooue his conſequence, be in the Scripture, or no. If they be, lett him bring them forth. Many of them queſtionles are drawne out of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, or grounded vpon humane reaſons. If they be not, the Miniſter which out of them inferres his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, doth not deduce it out of the pure word, or (which is all one) prooues not by conſequence dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of the pure and only word, that the Catholicke erreth, which was that he vndertooke; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer denieth his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of faith: for he drawes his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the word of God, and out of diuers propoſitions which are not in holie write. Is not this to flinch from their worde, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their articles of faith? or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do not the Miniſter &amp; his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith abuſe people, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing that which they neither do, nor canne performe.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:7766:20"/>
            <p>Behold a breefe, and eaſy methode to encounter all Miniſters and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries. Is it not obuious euen for thoſe, who are not ſtudents in deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to putt it in practiſe? There needs no more but eyes to ſee, and to vnderſtande English, to know if the pure word without additions, interpretations, or conſequences of others, do ſay ſuch a thing, or no. Do you not by this meanes euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceaue, that all the Miniſters are abuſers, and how the whole troope of Sectaries is miſledde? Yea I dare ſay double abuſers. For firſt the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter abuſeth men, in that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth by the pure word to shew them that, which he would haue them beleeue: next, that he will by the pure word lay open their errours pretended, and yett performeth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one, nor the other. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſters promiſing in their 31. and 5. articles to performe them both, and yet effecting neither, as by the forſaid practiſe is made euident;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7766:20"/> are impoſtours, and double impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours: as this methode, which euery Catholick may vſe, doth apparently declare. And ſo I haue fulfilled my promiſe, which was to lay downe a short and eaſie methode, by which all Catholiques may euidently shew that each Miniſter in all, and euery point of his pretended religion, is an abuſer, &amp; conſequently that all their followers are abuſed.</p>
            <p>This therfore is my aduice to all Sectaries, to thoſe eſpecially which ſeeke ſincerly theyr Saluation. Your Confeſſion promiſeth you the pure word of God, and you ſuppoſe that, according to that promiſe, there is nothing in your articles of fayth, which is not in the pure word; Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe this methode, and you ſhall euidently, and eaſily perceaue how you are abuſed. Place on the one ſyde the Principall articles of your faith, which I haue cited before. <hi>That original ſinne remaines after Baptiſme as it is a fault. That Ieſus Christ is our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7766:21"/> only Aduocate. That faith alone iuſtifieth,</hi> and which is cheefe of all. <hi>That the B. Sacrament is a figure of the body of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, which is eaten by faith.</hi> Then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer againſt each of theſe articles, ſet downe the textes, which are cited in the margent for eache of them (doubtles if you had any plaine text of Scripture, which taught that which is in that articles, it wold haue been coated in the margent) &amp; you shall cleerly ſee, that the pure word, ſetting aſide interpretations, and Miniſteriall conſequences, hath not that which is in your article: neither is there required ought but your eyes, and skill to reade, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that be in the pure word or no. And that your Miniſters preach, that the Scripture is eaſie, and that euery one there may learne his owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation; you vnderſtand I ame ſure ſignification of English: why then finde you not in the pure word that, which the Miniſters make you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue? Aſſure your ſelues if you find
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7766:21"/> it not, it is becauſe it is not there. Confront therfore the place cited in the margent of the article, with the article, and you shall ſee how egregiouſly you are mocked. And that you may ſee this more manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly, doe this following. Write in one line one article, or if it haue many partes, one only clauſe of the ſame. And if you finde any text of Scripture cited for that article, or peece therof, write in a ſecond line the words of the text cited, vnder the other line. If you find no text cited (as in many places there is not) put vnder the firſt line a cypher; for that if there were any text to authorize that article, it would be cited. This being donne, compare the firſt line with the ſecond: If you find in the ſecond line a cypher, you are cleerly coſened. If you find a text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſee if that, being preciſely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without medly of ſome thing els (that is to ſay, <hi>you muſt vnderſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ande; this ſignifieth; or the like;</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7766:22"/> that article propoſed; if it do not, know that you are deceaued. I my ſelf haue paralelled theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles with the textes alledged in the margent; take you but the like paines, and I will aſſure you that in ſteed of the pure word, you shall oft tymes finde a cypher; other tymes in the text cited you shall not find one worde of the article; and in breefe you shall not find there one article, or entiere clauſe of thoſe in Controuerſy between vs. Behold how you are deluded.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:7766:22"/>
            <head>ARTICLES OF THE CONFESSION OF FAITH OF the pretended reformed Churchs, confronted with the pure word of holy writt; Where it is euidently shewed, that the textes of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, euen in the Geneua Bible, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the margent of theſe arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, conteine nothing of that, which thoſe articles teach againſt the Catholick faith.</head>
            <head type="sub">which is A breefe &amp; eaſy meanes, by which euery Caluiniſt may manifeſtlie perceaue how he is abuſed, and wherby each Catholicke may shew the ſame vnto him.</head>
            <p>To ſaue you the paines (deceaued Countrymen) which I wished you to take, I haue heere confronted the articles of your faith controuerted, with the places cited in the marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, after the fashion before ſett downe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7766:23"/> and haue cited theſe textes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Geneua tranſlation, Compare them with me beginning at the 24. article.</p>
            <p>In this article, theſe clauſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are ſett downe without any text, cited in the margent, for proof of any of them; wherfore in ſteede of Scripture, I wil giue you vnder euery clauſe for proofe a Cypher.</p>
            <div n="24" type="article">
               <head>Article 24.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>VVe hold that Purgatory is an Illuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>By the abuſe and deceipt of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, Monaſticall vovves vvere introduced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Out of the ſame vvare-hovvſe proceeded Pilgrimages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Out of the ſame vvare-hovvſe vvas brought in Auricular Confeſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:7766:23"/>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Out of the ſame vvare-hovvſe ſprang Indulgenees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Out of the ſame vvare-hovvſe proceeded all other things, by vvhich vve thinke to merite grace and ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>VVe reiect all others meanes, vvhich men preſume to haue, to reconcile themſelues to God, as derogatory from the death, and paſsion of Ieſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>It is lavvfull for vs to pray but only according to that forme, vvhich God ſett dovvne in his vvord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p>In the 31. article you ſay. <hi>The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7766:24"/> of the Church in our times vvas interrupted, and hath failed; that God hath raiſed ſome after an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner to renevv the ſame, being ruinated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proofe. o.</p>
               <p>Behold how the Miniſters, and theyr Confeſſion of faith do abuſe you, and how often in one only ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle. They promiſe you, not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you but by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and propoſing vnto you all theſe clauſes to be beleeued, they prooue none of them by any text of Scripture, nor bring as much as one place of Scripture for confirmation of them. Examine the articles, you will finde more then a hundred clauſes as well affirmatiues, as nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, for proofe wherof there is no text coated, becauſe in deed they haue it not, iudge then if you be abuſed or no.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:7766:24"/>
               <p>And who, I pray you, can in equity accuſe another, vnles he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſome lawe commaunding, or prohibiting ſome thing violated by the party accuſed? Euery accuſation, commended to be truly an accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not a calumny, muſt be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the breach of ſome lawe, and accompanied with it proofes. Theſe Reformers doe not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, but making themſelues iudges, doe condemne of Superſtitions, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, and high treaſon againſt the deuine Maieſty, the holy Fathers, and vs all beſides in thoſe 8. poyntes ſett downe (and in diuers others which I omitt) pronouncing theyr bloody ſentence, by which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare both them and vs to be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, deceauers, inſtruments of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than in the promulgations of thoſe diuelish illuſions rehearſed. This ſentence pronounced, for execution of the ſame they haue ouerthrowen our Monaſteries; prophaned our holy places; and ſet fire on our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7766:25"/> Churches. Of what crime doe they accuſe vs, do they condemne vs? what deuine law doe they prooue to haue ben violated by vs? They neyther prooue, nor ſo much as cite any law, any letter of holy write, againſt which the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers &amp; we haue offended. And yet they accuſe vs, they condemne vs. Shameles wretches! but yet withall impudent liars! They promiſe, not to behaue themſelues but only as inſtruments of the holy Scripture, and not to propoſe ought but that; And yet they pronounce the eight forſayd ſentences, without citing one ſole paſſage of the Scripture. See, o you ſectaries, how palpably they abuſe you. But to ſee this more cleerly, and withall to take away from the Miniſters all meanes to circumuent you to your vtter ruine.</p>
               <p>Conſider with like attention that which enſueth. In the 5. arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle they wold make you beleeue, <hi>that the pure word, which is conteined in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7766:25"/> the bookes of holy Scripture, is the rule of all truth,</hi> and that nothing muſt be beleeued, but that which is in the pure word. This article is of great conſequence; for repoſing and grounding your ſelues vppon this, and not vppon any other thing, you reiect all the traditions of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church; you giue your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of condemnation againſt vs; you will not allow of <hi>neyther Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, nor Custome, nor Multitude, nor Humane wiſedome, nor Sentences, nor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions, nor Edicts, nor Lawes, nor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, nor Viſions, nor Miracles.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit all theſe make againſt your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, you make no bones thereof, you ſcorne them all, ſaying that you will nothing but the pure Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all the reſt proceeds from men ſubiect vnto errours; and <hi>that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things muſt be examined, ruled, and reformed according to the ſame pure word.</hi> This article therfore is of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence: and with good reaſon, to be beleeued, ought to be found in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7766:26"/> the holy Scripture; which if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters should frame in the force of their owne braynes, they deſerue doubtles to be banished all honeſt company, as men impudently bold, which ſeeke to make the world re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all things aboueſaid, for a propoſition of their owne inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and contradict themſelues: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing before ſaid, they would only carry themſelues as the organe of the wholy Scripture. Let vs therfore ſet downe in one line firſt the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, then vnder that the text, cited in the margent for proofe thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>Article 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The vvritten vvord is the rule of all truth:</hi> or els, as you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſay. <hi>Nothing is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, but that vvhich is in the vvritten vvord.</hi> In the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of this article you cite 4. textes for proofe of the contents.</p>
               <div n="1" type="text">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:7766:26"/>
                  <head>1. Text.</head>
                  <p>You shall not add any thing to the vvorde vvhich I commaunde, nor take any thing from the ſame. <hi>Saith Moyſes to the people of Iſrael.</hi> Deuter. 4. Verſ. 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="text">
                  <head>2. Text.</head>
                  <p>That vvhich I commaund you, that shall you doe, neither shall you adde any thing, nor diminish. Deut. 12. Verſ. 32.</p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>Heere is not any worde of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle in theſe paſſages, for you ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther finde <hi>(written word)</hi> nor <hi>(rule of all truth)</hi> which are the two termes of the article; wherfore this pure word doth not conteine that, which the article affirmeth. Lett vs weigh it more exactly. 1. Moyſes ſpake vnto the Iewes of that only, which he ordained, to witt of the Iudaicall law, and of no other. 2. he ſpake not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7766:27"/> of the written worde, of which alone the article is, but vniuerſally of the word. 3. Albeit he ſpake vnto Chriſtians, and of the only written word: haue we increaſed the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Moyſes? haue we added ought vnto them? 4. Thinke you that the <hi>Prophets</hi> compoſing new Scriptures, and ioyning them with the bookes of Moyſes, haue infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this precept? 5. if Moyſes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to beleeue any thing but that, which he ordayned; we muſt ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beleeue the Pſalmes of Dauid, nor the other <hi>Prophets,</hi> nor the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: for he ordained not that which theſe conteyne. Perceaue you not how ridiculous a thing it is, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this text, to verify by the pure word your article? which ſayth, <hi>the written word is the rule if all truth.</hi> The ſame article is prooued by an other paſſage. Galat. 1. Verſ. 8.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="text">
                  <head>3. Text.</head>
                  <p>Although vve, or an Angell from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7766:27"/> heauen preach othervviſe, then that vvhich vve haue preached vnto you, be he accurſed.</p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>In this text I neither read <hi>(writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word)</hi> nor <hi>(rule of all truth)</hi> which are the two termes of the article; wherefore the text hath not that, which the article teacheth. Nay it containes not one only word therof, come to the examen. 1. Is there in the text anie mention of the written word? of which onlie we diſpute, and the article ſpeakes of no other. 2. Who knoweth not that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calipſe was reuealed, and writt after that epiſtle of S. Paule? and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, which S. Paule euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, it alſo muſt be beleeued. Or is he which preacheth, and beleeueth the Apocalipſe accurſed? Or rather is S. Paule accurſed, who preached manie things afterward, which are not in that epiſtle to the Galathians? who is there of ſo ſmall capacitie,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7766:28"/> that in the reading of this chapter doth not ſee, that the word <hi>(other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe)</hi> is the ſame in ſenſe with <hi>(a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.)</hi> The Apoſtle, as it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt at the verie opening of the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, crieth out againſt thoſe, which togeather with the law of Chriſt, would ioyne Circumciſion againſt the doctrine of the Apoſtles. The wordes immediatlie going before, make the matter more cleere. <hi>I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile</hi> ſaith he to the Galat: 1. Verſ. 6. 7.8. <hi>that leauing him, who hath called you vnto the grace of Chriſt, you are ſo ſoone transferred vnto an other Ghoſpell: which is not another, vnles there be ſome that trouble you, &amp; will inuert the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt: But although we, or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from heauen preach to you otherwiſe then that, which we haue preached to you, be he accurſed.</hi> Is it not euident that S. Paul reiecteth that only, which is againſt that which he had preached? Then it is apparent alſo, that this text makes nothing for that, which the article contains to witt: <hi>That
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7766:28"/> the written word is the rule of all truth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The laſt paſſage, cited for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid article, is out of the Apocalipſe 22. Verſ. 18. in theſe wordes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="text">
                  <head>4. Texte.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I teſtifie to euerie one, hearing the vvordes of the prophecie of this booke. If any man shall add to theſe things, God shall adde vppon him the plagues vvritten in this booke. And if anie man shall diminish of the vvords of the booke of this prophecy, God shall take avvay his part out of the booke of life, and out of the holy Citty, and of theſe things that be vvritten in this booke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither do I reade in this paſſage <hi>(written word of the entyre Bible)</hi> of which only the Article intreats, nor <hi>(rule of all truth)</hi> wherfore the text ſayth not, <hi>that the pure word of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Bible is the rule of all truth,</hi> as the Article auerreth, rather the text
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7766:29"/> conſents not in one only terme with the article. Examine it. 1. Is it not manifeſt, that S. Iohn ſpake not but of the word conteyned in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calipſe? which the Miniſters will not allowe to be the rule of all truth; to what purpoſe then for proofe of that Article, <hi>That the pure word of the entire Bible is the rule of all truth, do</hi> they bring out this text? 2. if S. Iohn ſayd, that nothing muſt be added to that word of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calipſe in this ſenſe, and after this Miniſterial paraphraſe <hi>(that nothing muſt be beleeued which is not therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained)</hi> then he which should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Ghoſpell, the Epiſtles of S. Paul, of S. Iohn, and others, and the old teſtament, should be accurſed. Where were the Miniſters witts, thinke you, when to proue that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be bleeued, but that which is in the Bible, they alledged this paſſage? 3. To adde to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calipſe, is to thruſt in ſomthing as part of that ſacred booke: doe we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7766:29"/> doe ſo? What frantik people are your Miniſters? and you, o Caluiniſts? how groſſely doth your Confeſſion of fayth abuſe you, which treats you in ſuch a fashion, as if you had not eyes to reade, nor iudgment to vnderſtand the ſignification of one pure text? How many Miniſteriall gloſſes ar heere wanting, to make theſe textes ſpeake that, which this article contaynes? Lett vs go on.</p>
                  <p>Whence haue you, that the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the old and new Teſtament are holy Scripture? how know you that theſe bookes are Canonicall? <hi>By the inward perſuaſion of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſo you aunſweare in the 4. article <hi>That he makes vs decerne them from other Eccleſiaſticall bookes.</hi> It is not then by the holy Scripture that you know this, for your inward perſuaſion is not the written word. Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly it is falſe, <hi>That the pure word is the rule of all truth, and that all things must be examined, ruled, and reformed by the ſame.</hi> For it is not the rule of this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7766:30"/> and that of greateſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: to witt, that the bookes of the old and new Teſtament are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, and writen by deuine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation. Again, to reiect any booke from the number of the Canonicall (as for example you doe reiect that of Tobias, and admitt the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of S. Mathew) you guide not your ſelues by this rule of the pure word, but, as you giue it out, of the inward perſuaſion of the holy Ghoſt. See how your articles deſtroy each other. Tell me farther. Do you hold that one may, and ought to baptize little infants? That we muſt not rebaptize hereticques, which haue been baptized in the name of the B. Trinity; that we muſt keepe holy ſunday, and not ſaturday; you beleeue that the Mother of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned alwayes a virgin. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding you finde not one text of Scripture, to iuſtify any of theſe points; why do you then contradict your ſelues and your article, which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7766:30"/> teacheth, <hi>that the written word is the rule of all truth.</hi> Doth not S. Paul in the. 2. to the Theſſalon. 2. verſ. 15. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort ſaying. <hi>Stand, and hold faſt the instructions</hi> (our tranſlation reads traditions) <hi>which you haue learned ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by our word, or by our epiſtle.</hi> Note that he makes mention of the word beſides that, which is written in Scripture; and in the 2. to Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. 2. Verſ. 2. <hi>The things which thou haſt heard of me by many witneſſes, theſe commend to faythfull men, which shall be fitt to teach others alſo.</hi> Doe not you perceaue a diuine word, taught not by writing, but by word of mouth? In the. 1. to the Cor. 11. Verſ. 34. <hi>Other things I will ſet in order when I come.</hi> Such ordinances by word of mouth, are they not as well deuine as thoſe, which are ſett downe in writing? I omit many other autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities to this purpoſe, by the way only citing theſe, for that it is not my intent to iuſtify, and prooue vnto you in this treatiſe that, which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7766:31"/> we beleeue. My only ſcope is to shew vnto you, that you are abuſed; and that the pure word teacheth no ſuch thing, as your articles report. This haue I performed in this arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which I haue examined with the textes cited for the ſame; for the Article ſaith, that the written word is the rule of all truth; and in the paſſages alledged, we neyther read <hi>written word,</hi> nor <hi>the rule of all truth.</hi> Wherfore they haue not that which the article ſaith, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, knowing to reade, we should ſee it there. For concluſion heereof the Caluiniſts, in this article of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt importance, are therefore abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and by conſequence in all the reſt I before marked, which are out of this deduced againſt vs, which are in great number. Reuew them, and in ſo many points acknowledg your ſelues deceaued.</p>
                  <p>I haue at large examined this arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, aſwell for that, as hath been shewed, it is of greateſt importance;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7766:31"/> as alſo for that the falshood therof being diſcouered, the Miniſters are bereaued of the moſt efficatious, and ordinary meanes they had to defend themſelues, in theſe conflicts; for they alwayes fly for refuge to this Propoſition, <hi>That nothing must be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, bus that which is in the Scripture</hi> Their cuſtome is to queſtion vs, <hi>where finde you Purgatory in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? or the reall preſence of the body of Ieſus Chriſt in the ſacrament of the Altar &amp;c. For,</hi> ſay they, <hi>if it be not there, it is ſuperſtition to beleeue it.</hi> And by this meanes, in lieu of reforming our pretended abuſes by the pure word, they cunningly engage vs to prooue our faith. A wyly deuiſe. Catholicks looke vnto their fingers, and be ſure that when they make you ſuch que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, you take not vppon you to be diſputants: but allthough you haue many authorities, yett bring no place of Scripture to iuſtify your cauſe. Marke well the wilines of the Aduerſaries. They are bound
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7766:32"/> by their .31. article to reforme vs, and by their.5. to do it by the pure word: by this diſguiſe and faire apparence drawing many to their part. But their practiſe is after another fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion. For knowing well that they are neuer able to performe that, which they haue bound themſelues vnto, to diſingage themſelues from this obligation, by a fine deuiſe they endeuour to make vs the plaintifs, queſtioning vs after the fashion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid. And if in awnſwere of their queſtions, you bring ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe textes for your ſelf, behold, by this the Miniſter hath gott his neck out of the coller, and hauing before hand quitt himſelf of all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Fathers, Miracles &amp;c. he will turne of the Scripture at his owne pleaſure, and in fine delude you, though you haue ten cleere textes for your purpoſe: Of this we haue dayly experience. Handle him in an other fashion. You muſt neuer lett him change his coate. He is obliged
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7766:32"/> by the Confeſſion of his faith to shew you by the pure word your er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; hold him to it there to his teſtimonies of the pure word, which muſt ſett downe your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended errours; Doe but this, and I warrant you the Miniſter will quickly be brought vpon his knees; and haue a care you releaſe him not, but keepe him downe. But how? vrge him ſtill with this, that he shew you ſome expreſſe text of Scripture which ſayth, <hi>That there is no Purgatory;</hi> or <hi>That, the body of Ieſus Christ is not in the Eucharist.</hi> It is his charge to do it, who hath pawned his word to shew vs by the pure word our errours. But if he hope to ſcape the torture by this ſleight, ſaying that he ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sheweth our errour in that (as he ſayth) we cannot shew by the Scripture Purgatory, or the reall preſence: Haue a care, that though you haue many cleere textes on your ſide, bring none, make not your ſelues Plaintifs, for ſo he will
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7766:33"/> be deliuered from the rack; but preſſe him eagrely that he shw you that he promiſed, or at leaſt, <hi>that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be beleeued but that, which is in the Scripture</hi> (for by this maxime alone doth he argue you of errour) And then that after he hath donne this, you will produce your places. Not being able to shew this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in the whole Scripture (as by the precedent examen I haue shewd he cannot) he is driuen to a non plus, nor hath he any meanes to ſcape a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Thus shall you shew breefly &amp; euidently, that their 31. and 5. articles ar falſe, which promiſed to reforme our pretended abuſes by the pure word, and cannot do it: And that the Mimiſters are egregious impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, which vnder ſuch a faire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text haue ſeduced ſo many thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of ſoules. And you of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended religion, put but your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to this triall, and you will ſee them preſently fall ſpeechles, and your ſelues apparently abuſed.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:7766:33"/>
                  <p>Before we paſſe any farther, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not omitt to examine breeflie one clauſe of the 24. article, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let paſſe, for that for it there is cited in the margent a texte, which is not donne in the other clauſes.</p>
                  <p>An other clauſe of the 24. article.</p>
                  <q>Out of the vvare-hovvſe of the deuill, proceede the forbidding to marrie, and the free vſe of meates, and the ceremonious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of ſome daies.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>In the last times certaine shalt depart from the faith, attending to ſpirits of errours, forbidding to marry, commaunding to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from meates, vvhich God created for the faithfull, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue them vvith thanks giuing, for euerie creature of God is good, and nothing to be reiected. <hi>1. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth. 4. Verſ. 3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:7766:34"/>
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>By this clauſe the Article ſeemes to reprehend the Catholicque Church, but wrongfullie. For. 1. shee forbids not to marrie, otherwiſe no Catholick could be married, but that he muſt breake the precept of the Church; shee onlie cauſeth that to be kept, which God in his Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures commaundeth: to witt, that men fulfill their vowes, and for this cauſe that Preeſts, and others which haue vowed chaſtity, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie, obſerue their vowes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it followeth that they may not marrie. Neither doth the text alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſay ought to the contrarie. 2. I admire the little iudgment of the Miniſters; doe they thinke that the Phyſitians <hi>commaunding</hi> their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients <hi>to abſtaine from ſome meates</hi> for a time to recouer their health, doe goe againſt the Apoſtle, and <hi>teach a deuilish doctrine?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I ame more amazed at the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of theſe men, whoe reading
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7766:34"/> the prohibition of ſome meates made by the Apoſtles, gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather in the 1. Councell. Act. 15. verſ. 28. in theſe wordes <hi>It hath ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med good to the Holy Ghoſt and to vs, to lay no further burden vppon you, then theſe neceſſary things.</hi> Among other things <hi>that you abſtaine from bloud and that which is ſtrangled.</hi> They dare, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing the text cited, ſay, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out execrable blaſphemy, againſt the holy Apoſtles, and againſt the holy Ghoſt. <hi>That from the ware-howſe of the diuell proceedeth the prohition of ſome meates;</hi> terming heereby the holy Ghoſt ſathan, and the firſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Councell of the Apoſtles, the ware-howſe of the deuill, and theyr prohibition an abuſe and illuſion. S. Paul, which aſſiſted at that ſacred Councell, is farr of from cenſuring in that manner that precept, which he with the reſt had decreed <hi>to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from certayn meates.</hi> But forſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that there wold come hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, that wold forbidde mariage as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7766:35"/> a thing in it ſelf vnlawfull, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by the deuill; and ſome meates as naught in themſelues and of their owne nature (ſo did the Maniche, Marcion and Tatian, as S. Auguſtine, with others recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) theſe the Apoſtle condemneth. The Church is farr diſtant from this errour. Thus doe S. Auguſtine, S. Chriſoſtome, S. Hierome, and S. Ambroſe expound this place; and the reaſon which the Apoſtle brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth for his condemnation contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe words, <hi>euery creature of God is good,</hi> doth authorize the ſame. And it belongs to the Miniſter, who is plaintife, to prooue the contrarie. Finally, the Church doth not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutelie commaund to abſtaine from meates, for it forbiddeth not fish, whice is meate; nor at all times, but onlie certaine particular meates, and at certaine times; which thing the Apoſtle reprehends not, who ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of theſe, who abſolutelie <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde to abſtaine from meates,</hi> and that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7766:35"/> without limitation to any times. 3. for the proofe of the 3. clauſe of the obſeruation of daies, the article hath cited no texte, in that therfore it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth.</p>
                     <p>An other clauſe of the 24. article.</p>
                     <q>IESVS CHRIST is giuen vs for the ſole Aduocate: All that vvhich men haue imagined about the interceſsion of Saintes departed, is nought els but an abuſe and deceipt of Sathan.</q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>The onlie pointe of controuerſie between vs in the firſt clauſe of this article, is of the word <hi>(ſole)</hi> for thes two textes are cited in margent, for the ſecond clauſe nothing, the firſt in the 1. Timoth. 2.5.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Texte.</head>
                  <p>There is one only God, and one onlie mediatour betvveen God and men, man IESVS CHRIST.</p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:7766:36"/>
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>I will ſet downe the texte entier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to make it more cleere that he ſaith not that, which the article tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: behold the Apoſtles wordes.</p>
                     <q>God vvill that all men be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and come to the knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of truth, for there is one only God, and one only media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour betvveene God and men, man IESVS CHRIST vvho gaue himſelfe for reedmption of all.</q>
                     <p>I finde not in this paſſage alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the termes <hi>(of Aduocate, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſsion)</hi> of which we debate, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther finde I thar Saints are shutt out from that office of Aduocate, as ſaith the article. And if the Miniſter ſay that the name of mediatour, as S. Paul vnderſtands it, is the ſame with Aduocate; I aunſweare firſt, that the Miniſter, or rather his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, muſt prooue that the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7766:36"/> name of mediatour is taken for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, and Aduocate by interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and not for mediatour and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate by redemption; He I ſay muſt prooue this, and that by the pure word alone, otherwiſe the place alledged conſenteth not with the Confeſſion of faith, neither doth it reiect the interceſſion of Saintes. 2. I make aunſweare (which by the place entirely cited doth appeare) that S. Paul ſpake of one Mediatour (they are the Apoſtles owne words) who <hi>hath giuen himſelfe a redemption for all:</hi> of ſuch a Mediatour he ſaith that he is one alone, neither doe the Catholickes teach that the Saintes are ſuch mediatours. This paſſage therfore prooues nothing againſt Catholicques, neither doth it ſay that IESVS CHRIST is giuen vs for our ſole Aduocate, nor that to beleeue the interceſſion of Saints is an abuſe, and deceipt of the deuill. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. This word <hi>(ſole)</hi> hath beene ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Miniſters in the Geneua
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:7766:37"/> Bible for it is neither in the Greeke nor Latin texte: and S. Paule to the Galat. 3. calleth Moyſes Mediatour.</p>
                     <p>The ſeconde paſſage, alledged for this clauſe in their Confeſſion, is in the 1. epiſtle of S. Iohn. 2. Verſ. 1.2.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="text">
                  <head>2. Texte.</head>
                  <p>Theſe things I vvrite vnto you, that you ſinne not. But &amp; if any one ſinne, vve haue an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate vvith the Father, <hi>IESVS</hi> Chriſt the iuſt: for he is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſinnes, and not for ours only; but alſo for thoſe of the vvhole vvorlde.</p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>Is it not manifeſt, that he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not of euery Aduocate, but of an Aduocate which is a propitiation for the ſinnes of the whole world, to witt by the effuſion of his bloud? The Catholicques hold not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch Aduocate, but our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. To what purpoſe then is it to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7766:37"/> bring this paſſage, which toucheth not that which is in controuerſie? And marke well that it is the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters parte, who is Plaintife, to shew that the name of Aduocate is heere taken for anie interceſſour, euen him, who is not a propitiation for the ſinnes of the world by his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and all this by the pure worde. 2. Beſides, if the Miniſter will perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naciouſly vnderſtand by the name of Aduocate him, who is not a propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for the ſinnes of the world which is of his owne head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the pure word, yea againſt the pure word alledged.) This word <hi>only</hi>) of which wee only ſtriue, not being in this text, this place vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eth not this article <hi>that IESVS Chriſt only Aduocate.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let vs come to the 20. Article.</p>
                     <p>Theſe are the wordes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="article">
               <head>Article. 20.</head>
               <p>VVe beleeue that vve are made partakers of that iuſtice
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7766:38"/> 
                  <hi>(to witt Chriſtian)</hi> by faith alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Textes cited in the Margent of this Article.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Man is iustified by faith, vvithout the vvorkes of the lavve. <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom. 3. Verſ. 28.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>Man is not iuſtified by the vvorkes of the Lavve, but only by the faith of IESVS Chriſt. <bibl>
                        <hi>Galat. 2. Verſ. 16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before faith came vve vvere kept vnder the lavv, shut vp vnto that faith vvhich vvas to be reuealed. Therfore the lavve vvas our Pedago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue in Christ, that vve might be iuſtified by faith, but vvhen that faith is come novv vve are not vnder a Pedagogue <bibl>
                        <hi>Galat. 3. Verſ. 23.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <div type="examination">
                  <head>Examen.</head>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:7766:38"/>
                  <p>I reade not one word, in all theſe textes, of the workes of Chriſtian faith, of which alone, and of no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers we ſpeake, and hold neceſſary to iuſtification. It is manifeſt that this pure word alledged, ſpeaketh of workes of the Iudaicall religion, ſtyled commonly by S. Paul by the name of the Lawe, and not of the workes of Chriſtian Religion. Theſe paſſages therfore ſay onlie, that Chriſtian faith without Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and other ceremonies of the Iewes, doth iuſtifie. Who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth this? is this all one, or as much as to ſay that Chriſtian faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the workes, which proceed from the ſaid faith in IESVS Chriſt, as is penance, doth iuſtifie? Which is that the article teacheth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this pure worde ſeconds not that which the article ſayeth. I am amazed at the impudency, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Miniſters: S. Paul diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing ſo largely in fiue whole chapters of that epiſtle to the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7766:39"/> againſt thoſe which would ioyne with Chriſtian faith Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and other workes of Iudaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; and the very titles of thoſe chapters in the Geneua tranſlation noting the ſame: yet the aduerſaries will alledge theſe againſt them, who hold that Chriſtian workes are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to iuſtification. Open but the epiſtle, and thou wilt deteſt ſuch abuſers; the whole epiſtle sheweth that which I ſay. It shall ſuffiſe for proofe heereof to cite the words of the. 5. chapter. 2. verſe. <hi>Behold I tell you, that if you be circumciſed, Chriſt shall proffit you nothing, and I teſtifie againe to euerie man circumciding himſelf, that he is a debter to doe the whole law; you are euacuated from Chriſt, that are iuſtified in the law. You are fallen from grace, for we by faith exſpect the hope of iuſtice. In IESVS Christ neither circumciſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth ought, uor prepuce, but faith wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by charity.</hi> Do not you falſefye? doth not S. Paul teach in theſe laſte wordes the contrarie to your arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle?
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7766:39"/> The Apoſtle oppoſeth Chriſtian Religion, which is called faith in Chriſt, vnto the Iudaicall religion, which is named the lawe; and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that this later is not neceſſary to iuſtification, but that the former ſuffiſeth, and doth not oppoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith to Chriſtian workes. The laſt texte cited for the foreſaid arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, hath as little energy as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents. it is this of S. Iohn 3. Verſ. 15.16.</p>
                  <q>As Moyſes exalted the Serpent in the deſert, ſo must the ſonne of man be exalted, that euerie one vvhich belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him, perish not, but may haue life euerlaſting. For ſo God loued the vvorld, that he gaue his only begotten ſonne, that euery one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth in him, perish not, but haue life euerlasting.</q>
                  <p>The word <hi>(only)</hi> of which only
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7766:40"/> is our variance, and which is in your article, teaching that faith only iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth, is not in this text: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this, vnles you add thereto the word <hi>(only)</hi> makes nothing to your purpoſe; and how often doth this ſpeech, <hi>to beleeue in IESVS Chriſt,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie <hi>to profeſſe the Ghoſpell, and liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame?</hi> for <hi>faith,</hi> ſaith S. Iames in the 1. chapter 17. verſe. <hi>If it haue not workes is dead.</hi> Doth not S. Paul. Galat. 5. Verſ. 6. ſay that <hi>that which iuſtifieth is faith, working by cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie?</hi> Doth not our Sauiour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce this ſentence; if thou wilt enter into life keepe the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements? But I am not bound to prooue, that faith alone without Chriſtian workes doth not iuſtifie, it is you that are engaged to prooue by the pure worde, that that <hi>alone</hi> doth iuſtifie; <hi>alone,</hi> I ſay, for of that <hi>alone</hi> doe we diſpute. In the 11. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle it is ſaid that.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <head>Article 11.</head>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:7766:40"/>
               <p>Originall ſinne after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is ſtill ſinne, as it is a fault; hovvbeit the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation thereof is taken avvay in the children of God, vvho of his mercifull goodnes doth not impute it vnto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In proofe of this is alledged one only place in the margent. Rom. 7. Verſ. 7.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Texte.</head>
                  <p>VVhat shall vve ſay then? is the lavve ſinne? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, but ſinne I did not knovv, but by the lavve, for concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence I knevv not, vnles the lavv did ſay, thou shalt not couet.</p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>Here is not in the text one word contained in the article; wherefore this Confeſſion, promiſing to ſay nothing but by the pure word, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7766:41"/> vs in this point. Go on.</p>
                     <p>Let vs examine the 36. and 37. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, which ſpeake of the B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: which ſince it is obſcurely ſpoken of, for more perſpicuity I will borrow ſomewhat out of your Catechiſme.</p>
                     <p>The 1. clauſe of the 36. article.</p>
                     <q>VVe teſtifie that the Supper is a teſtimonie of the vnitie, vvhich vve haue vvith IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS Chriſt; vvhoſe body <hi>(you ſay in your Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme in the 53. leſſon or Sunday)</hi> is not included vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bread, nor his bloud vvithin the chalice, that vve muſt not ſeeke him in theſe corruptible elementes. <hi>For proofe you alleadge this texte.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>The cuppe of benediction
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:7766:41"/> vvhich vve do bleſſe, is it not the communion of the bloud of Chriſt? and the bread vvhich vve do breake, is it not the communion of the bodie of Chriſt? for being manie, vve are one only bread, and one only body, for vve all partake of one only bread. <hi>1. Corinth. 10. Verſ. 16.17.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I reade not in this text</hi> (teſtimony of the vnity with IESVS Chriſt) <hi>the text therfore agrees not with the article. But I reade</hi> communion of bloud, communion of body, <hi>which is a different matter from</hi> testimony of vnity with IESVS Christ, <hi>and she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth</hi> that the body of IESVS Christ may be founde in theſe corruptible ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>vnder the accidents of bread and wine; which this article de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>An other clauſe of the ſame article</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:7766:42"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In the ſupper are</hi> Signss, which te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify that the body and bloud of IESVS Chriſt, ſerueth no leſſe for the ſoule to eate and drinke, then bread and wine doth for the body. <hi>Theſe Articles ſay not in expreſſe termes that</hi> the body of IESVS Chriſt is not in the Euchariſt <hi>to couer with obſcurity theyr errour; to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe this darknes I muſt borrow ſome light from theyr Catechiſme in the 53. leſſon.</hi> we muſt not <hi>(ſayth it)</hi> vnderſtand that the body is incloſed within the bread, nor the bloud within the chalice; but contrariwiſe, to haue the verity of this ſacrament, we muſt lift vp our hartes on high to heauen, where IESVS Chriſt is, and not ſeeke him in theſe corruptible elements. <hi>For this clauſe you cite two textes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="text">
                  <head>1. Texte.</head>
                  <p>I am the liuing bread, that came dovvne from heauen: if any man eate of this bread, he shall liue for euer, and the bread vvhich I vvill giue is
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:7766:42"/> my flesh, vvhich I vvill giue for the life of the vvorld. <hi>Iohn. 6. Verſ. 51.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>Firſt I reade not in this text <hi>(ſignes which testify)</hi> but this expreſſely, that <hi>Chriſt is the liuing bread,</hi> not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread made of flowre, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; but <hi>which is his flesh,</hi> which ſayth he, <hi>I will giue for the life of the world;</hi> As alſo in the geuing of it he ſayd, Take, <hi>This is my body, which shalbe giuen for you.</hi> Was it a ſigne, or figure of his body, which was nayled one the croſſe: was it not his proper body? This clauſe then is falſe. 2. The miniſters, whoe haue promiſed to propoſe nothing but the pure Scripture, how doe they thruſt vppon vs this clauſe ſo wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty, <hi>The body of IESVS Chriſt is not contained, and included within the bread, nor the blood &amp;c.</hi> Without any writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word? ſee theyr fraude, and how well they keepe theyr word
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:7766:43"/> in a matter of greateſt moment.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="text">
                  <head>2. Texte.</head>
                  <p>IESVS tooke bread, and hauing giuen thankes brake it, and ſaid take, eate. This is my bodie, vvhich is broken for you; do this in commemoration of me. In like manner after ſupper he tooke the cuppe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this cuppe is the nevv te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in my blood, this do ye, as often as you shall drinke therof in remembrance of me. <hi>1. Corinth. 11. Verſ. 24.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>Examen.</head>
                     <p>Who can finde out in this texte. <hi>Signes which teſtify; figure; ſigne of the body of IESVS Christ; which is not in the bread, nor the bloud in the chalice?</hi> all which the article teacheth. The text then helpes them nothing; nay how could the text more cleerly reiect the aduerſaries beleefe, which is <hi>that the body is not vnder the bread
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:7766:43"/> nor the bloud within the chalice.</hi> Let the Caluiniſtes conſider if they be abuſed or no: The Miniſters haue entred bondes to shew by the pure word, That the ſupper <hi>is a ſigne which tesſtifieth, a figure of the body of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, which is not vnder the bread, and of the bloud which is not within the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice:</hi> and to cancell theyr obligations, they bring for paiment this texte of Scripture, in which (being it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten downe) if you reade it not, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you want your ſight, or they deceaue you. Rather ſee you not the contrary? then ſay they are dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled iuglers.</p>
                     <p>An other clauſe of that Article.</p>
                     <p>After affirming that IESVS Chriſt doth nourish, and quicken vs with the ſubſtance of his body, and of his bloud, that which the Catholic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes beleeue alſo; they add, (in which we diſagree) without aled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging any texte for the ſame (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore put vnderneath for proofe a cypher as before.)</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:7766:44"/>1. <hi>VVe hold notvvithstanding, that this is donne ſpiritually.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Proofe. o.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſupper is a figure of the body,</hi> or, <hi>In the ſupper is figured the bodie of IESVS Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Proofe. o.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Becauſe the miſterie of this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is celeſtiall, it cannot be taken but by faith,</hi> or to vſe their vulgar phraſe, <hi>by the mouth of faith: Thoſe vvhich bring vvith them a pure faith as a veſſell, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue trulie that vvhich the ſignes teſtifie;</hi> commonlie they ſay, <hi>That in the ſupper is eaten the bodie of IESVS Christ by the mouth of faith</hi> and in the 53. Sunday of their Catechiſme, it is ſaid, <hi>to haue the veritie of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:7766:44"/> the Sacrament, vve muſt lift vp our hartes to heauen vvhere it is.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Proofe. o.</p>
                     <p>Behold many articles, and of greate conſequence proued by a Cypher. Behold how you are abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The Miniſters make you beleeue all this, not being able to shew for it any texte of Scripture. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence will be, that your ſupper is purely their owne inuention: This by your principles I shew. For you haue no pure textes which ſay that, which you affirmatiuely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue of the ſupper, of which you hold thoſe three thinges aforeſayd principally. <hi>It is figure &amp;c. that by the mouthe of fayth the body eateh &amp;c.</hi> you should diſtinctly ſett downe that, which of our fayth you deny in this matter, from that which therein you poſitiuely beleeue: for how be it that we did erre (of which I haue shewed the contrary) and that your
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:7766:45"/> negatiue propoſitions <hi>IESVS Chriſt is not in the Euchariſt, and the like</hi> were true; it followeth not that that, which you affirmatiuely beleeue, moſt needes be true; and that you erre not therein. Becauſe one goeth wrong one way, is he, which takes an other, certaine to goe right? may not both be out of their way? Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine therfore your aſſertions, and you finde not any shew of textes that teache, <hi>that the ſupper is a figure of the body &amp;c.</hi> nor which <hi>ſpeake of the mouth of faith.</hi> Conſequently your whole ſupper is a humane inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which being ſo, in my opinion in the eating a good capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or a cock, you may more eaſely remember the death of the ſonne of God, for that therein is made mention of the cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing of a cock; then in eating a bit of bread. For which cauſe you shall do more prudently, to make of them a figure &amp; memorie, then of a peece of bread; which is no more holie, then that you eate commonlie at
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:7766:45"/> your table.</p>
                     <p>It may be that ſome Caluiniſte, thinking himſelfe better skilled in the Scriptures, then the Miniſters which compoſed the Confeſſion of faith, and cited for proofe therof thoſe ſacred textes they iudged moſt fauourable, will vrge, to prooue <hi>the ſupper to be a figure,</hi> that, which our Sauiour ſaid Iohn. 6. Verſ. 63. <hi>It is the ſpirit which quickeneth, the flesh proffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing, the words which I ſpeake vnto you are ſpirit and life.</hi> For awn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. 1. You muſt vnderſtand, that your Miniſters are at variance, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the 6. of S. Iohn anie thing be ſpoken of the ſupper. Caluin in the fourth booke of his Inſtit. cap. 17. §. 33. Kemnicius, and Zuinglius deny it. How then will you eſtablish this firme article of your faith vpon ſo weake a foundation, doubted of by theſe of your owne faction? How can you ſerue your ſelues of that paſſage againſt vs, either for your figure, or for your <hi>Spiritually?</hi>
                        <pb n="90" facs="tcp:7766:46"/> 2. I reade not in this text <hi>figure:</hi> and if anie one ſay that <hi>ſpiritt</hi> and <hi>figure</hi> is all one; I may not beleeue him without his proofe, and that by the pure Scripture. And who perceaues not how ridiculous this deuiſe is? the diuells are ſpirites, are they fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures? the Angells and our ſoules are ſpirittes? are they alſo figures? God himſelf is he not a moſt pure ſpiritt? is he a figure? it belongs not to me to explicate this place. I only shew that the pure word ſaith not that, which the article conteineth, &amp; conſequently the Miniſters mock vs. Yet by the way, knowe that the ſenſe of this texte is, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour would not giue vs to eate his flesh dead, and in peeces (as we eate of the ordinarie flesh, as the Caphar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naites imagined) to eate of flesh in this manner, proffitteth nothing to ſaluation; but flesh animated by his ſpirite, and quickened by his deuine life: in this manner we eate it. In which fashion we cannot eate anie
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:7766:46"/> other flesh, for it muſt firſt be dead, before it nourish vs. Remember finally that I doe not by this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture prooue my faith, this ſuffiſeth me, that in theſe words you reade not <hi>either figure of body, or that we hold that it is donne ſpiritually, in ſuch manner that the body is not contained there,</hi> this, I ſay, ſuffiſeth to make you know you are miſledd. For ſince you reade it not, (which doubtles if it were there, you might) the pure word warranteth not that which this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle containeth.</p>
                     <p>Behold Syr the arte, which in this letter I promiſed to diſcouer vnto you: is it not a rare &amp; worthy hunting-game? haue you ere this ſeene ſuch courſing? F. Veron in teaching it me, told me that, which I know will giue it no ſmall luſter in your eye: that he receaued the origine, and ſubſtance therof from the R.F. Gontery, which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous hunter was the authour, and inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of this ſo efficacious, and facile ſport; who alſo vſed no other in his diſputes a-againſt the Miniſters, iudging this the beſt, and moſt powerfull of all. And you know well, that that fearfull ſcourge of the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke is moſt expert in theſe combats <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="92" facs="tcp:7766:47"/> being ſo beaten a ſoldiour in thoſe warres, each prudent man wil make a great eſteme of his aduiſe herein. He hath putt to ſlight the Miniſters of Dieppe, of Caen, of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan &amp;c. and among the reſt ſome Allmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he founde at Tourlac. But how? Truly by no other meanes but this, by the pure Scripture alone, and that after the Geneua Tranſlation, by the practiſe before ſet downe: Sauing that he brideled them in more shortly, for he neuer ſuffered them in any point debated, to proceed by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, which they ſaid they would deduce out of the Scripture, vnles they firſt ſubſcribed, that they could not enter combate with vs by the pure written word.</p>
                     <p>I should now ſende you the relation promiſed of this Conference, between F. Veron, and the Miniſter Hucher, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the printer, by reaſon of the great froſtes could not diſpatch the ſame ſo ſoone, as I hoped; not to keepe you wholy in ſuſpence, I ſend you the ſummary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, togeather with the meanes to buckle with the Sectaries. The whole Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is vnder the preſſe, you shall haue it within eight daies; ioyne it to this fashion of hunting which I now ſend you, for in that you will ſee the practiſe of this kinde of chace, vſed by the Father in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict. Heere will you alſo ſee, by this ſo
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:7766:47"/> ſuccesfull and remarkable victory, the efficacy of this arte. It is ſcarcely poſſible to putt a man to more confuſion, then the Miniſter was in. The fame of this victory ſtrooke the ſectaries to the harte. Seeing the title of this epiſtle before it was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they were much offended at it, but all partes thereof are eaſily iuſtified, by the Actes of the Conference ſigned. Behold out of them the Miniſters owne wordes. He hauing promiſed to shew by the pure word, that IESVS Chriſt is not in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, after a little preſſing ſaid; <hi>The truth is, that theſe vvords (the body of IESVS Chriſt is not in the Euchariſt) are not in the Scripture.</hi> And after being vrged a little harder, he confeſſed beſides twice, before all the aſſembly, that he had not any text in Scripture, which, ſetting aſide all conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, conteyned formally and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſenſe of this propoſition. <hi>IESVS Chriſt is not in the Euchariſt,</hi> which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he before vndertooke to shew by the pure word; and ſo to reforme the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite in his errour. Is not this as much as to confeſſe, that he could not by the pure word reforme vs in this point? is not this to forſake it? is not this to renounce the office and exerciſe of a reformer? thinke you theſe fittes proceede from a merry hart? wherfore with reaſon the epiſtle beares for title <hi>The Miniſter of Amiens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:7766:48"/> to renounce the pure vvord of holy vvrite:</hi> He ſtayed ſo long dumme, and in preſence of ſo many perſonnes, and of ſuch quality, that there is no tergiuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and refuſed ſo long time in the third ſeſſion, to come to the proofe of that, in which the day before he was ſtruck ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, or alſo to deale in any other point; that the flight is as euident, as the day light. VVherfore the epiſtle hath right vnto his title. VVithin few dayes you shall ſee the narration at large, well ſubſcribed and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; in the meane tyme notwithſtanding, for iuſtification of the ſummary thereof, ſett downe in the beginning of this letter, I haue procured theſe ſubſcriptions follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <head>Subſcriptions of the Conference, the ſumme vvherof is contained in the beginning of this letter.</head>
            <p>VVEE the ſubſigned Gentlemen of the Duke of Longueuille, being preſent with our ſaid Lord at the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, of which the narration is before ſet downe, do teſtifie that they haue truly paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as it is declared. Giuen at Amyens the 12. of February. 1615.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Pelletot, Foucaucourt, Le Cheualier de Moyencourt, Gondreuille, Tannere, Gouſtimenil, Courtauenel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:7766:48"/>
            <head>Certaine poincts collected out of this practiſe, and other experiences of this kind, reduced to ſix heads, for the more warie proceeding of Catholiques with Sectaries of our age.</head>
            <p>THE 1. poinct. Seeing that our new Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries doe ſuppoſe vs Catholiques to be deceaued, in our beleefe, and that they ar ſent to reforme vs by the <hi>onlie vvritten vvord of Scripture,</hi> er the Catholique enter into conference with anie Sectarie, let him firſt demaund what he vnderſtandeth by the <hi>onlie vvritten vvord of Scripture:</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Old and new Teſtament, with all the parts of eche both, as we Catholiques doe; or els what? Then let the Catholique requeſt the Sectarie to proue by the <hi>onlie vvritten vvord,</hi> as he tooke vppon him, that the whole Bible, or ſuch parcels as he doth admit for holie Scripture, or reiect, ar in deede, or at not holy Scripture. He cannot doe it; but by Tradition, and by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church her authoritie.</p>
            <p>The 2. is. No Catholique conferring, muſt ſeeke to proue our opinions, which the Sectaries diſalowe of; for we ar in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and defendants, not plainetifes.</p>
            <p>The 3. is. The Catholique muſt not in any caſe permit the Sectarie to bring anie proofe whatſoeuer, other then the <hi>onlie vvritten vvord of Scripture,</hi> and this alſo
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:7766:49"/> without anie interpretation, gloſe, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of his owne braine.</p>
            <p>The 4. is Let not the Catholique ſuffer his Aduerſary to leape from pale to pearch, and from one Controuerſie to another, vntill he be conuinced of errour in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and this by the <hi>onlie vvritten vvord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 5. is. The Sectarie not proouing by the <hi>onlie vvritten vvord,</hi> that which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, as not able to performe it; the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique muſt conſtraine ether him, or ſome els there preſent, to ſubſcribe that he could not prooue what he vndertooke, in ſuch ſort, as he ought to haue donne.</p>
            <p>The 6. and laſt is. The Catholique muſt confer, and conſider with attention the places of Scripture, alledged by Sectaries to diſproue our doctrine; for ordinarilie they make no more to the purpoſe, then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to a nut. For example to prooue <hi>that vve muſt beleeue the onlie vvritten vvord:</hi> they bring forth theſe places. Deuter 4. v. 2. Deuter. 12. v. 32. Galat. 1. v. 8. Apocalip. 22. v. 18. which make nothing againſt vs, or for them. For by the firſt and ſecond, we ſhould, according to the ſenſe of our aduerſaries, beleeue nought els, but that which is in the Deuteronomie; by the third, nothing but that epiſtle of S. Paul; by the laſt, nought els but the Apocalipſe. See theire madnes, and foolery, and looke to theire water.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
